researchers just published a paper in
which they kept brain organoids, yes,
tiny human brains that you can grow in a
jar if you want to, alive for five
years. Now, if you are not familiar, and
if you watch my content, you are
probably really familiar. You can take a
skin cell or you can harvest fetal brain
tissue and you can turn it into a tiny
brain. There's a lot of ways to make
them and a lot of reasons why you would
want to. For the most part, they're made
from B cells or skin tissue. the US,
it's a little bit hard to harvest fetal
brain tissue. You can take a cell, turn
it into a stem cell by giving it the
right media, and gently coax it into
becoming brain tissue. Yes, those are
tiny eyes. Yes, they work. They're
essentially the optic cups that we would
have because eyes are part of our
nervous system. They're largely used to
test medications and model diseases. You
could even have your own little brain
organoid made so they could test
medications on you prior to giving it to
you. also very valuable for things like
brain tumors. Allison Motri at UC San
Diego actually grew Neanderthal brain
organoids from Neanderthal cells which
is wild but there is a subset of
researchers who want to use them for
computation because they are much less
energy hungry than standard models but
there's a long way to go there. The more
complicated they are the better they are
at computation and some researchers have
claimed sentience. But back to our
friends who kept them alive for 5 years.
This is absolutely unprecedented. And
for the longest time, people had thought
it was because of oxygenation because
they would end up suffering from hypoxia
and they wouldn't live very long. But
researchers have managed to keep them
alive by allowing their nerves to fire.
Yes. It turns out that one of the big
problems for why they would atrophy is
that they eventually just kind of gave
up because the media did not support the
nervous system functioning. they would
essentially eventually give up. When you
put them in a media that has oxygen, has
food, but also supports neural firing
rather than just tampering it, it
worked. They didn't atrophy. The
experiment ended after 5 years, but they
could have kept them alive longer. Now,
researchers did know that at the early
stages when you're growing a brain, they
look very much like a preterm baby. But
the longer they are kept alive, the more
they look like their actual
chronological age. They also found out
that the cells knew how old they were.
They had memory of their time spent. So
essentially by the time they got to be 5
years old, their gene expression was
such that it matched what a human
toddler would look like, at least in
terms of their genes. They also
developed age related cell types. This
part is really important to medicine and
maybe robotics. When they made chimeas,
so mixed the aged cells with younger
ones and turned them into a new brain
organoid blob, the older cells
remembered their age. They continued to
have the age related markers and the
younger ones didn't. They behaved as
though they were prenatal. Now brain
organoids do have brain waves and in the
beginning when people just started to
research them they only had delta brain
waves. So the ones that are associated
with sleep or being comeosse as they age
they do start to get more complex brain
waves. So it's not just delta the kind
that's associated with being asleep. I
would like to provide the caution that
this does not mean that they are
conscious. I mean, consciousness is a
pretty high bar. People don't even want
to say that cats and dogs are conscious.
The traditional demonstration of
consciousness requires somebody to
recognize themselves in a mirror,
although even fish can do that. So, it's
it's a strange way that we can provide
an explanation for consciousness. I'm
going to roll with the medical
definition. So, aware, awake, alert.
Now, they do have eyes, so maybe one day
they could develop and recognize
themselves in a mirror. Although that is
a very scary thought. I wonder if we
could put them in a robot and give that
robot vision and see if they could
recognize themselves. One day, one day
we will all approach these questions.
I'll probably be the one telling you
about it. Yes, they do have activity
that you would expect in a brain. So,
theta, alpha, beta, gamma, brain waves,
things that you would associate more
with a wakeful state. They do better
when they're dropped into game world.
These guys had them play Pong. And since
then, they've operated a number of
robots, spider robots, snake robots,
other things. I would really like to see
a long-term study of their brain waves
as they are playing a video game. And
yes, researchers do believe that they
have the building blocks necessary for
memory. And in game world, it's been
seen that they have both long-term and
short-term memory, so long as they are
reinforced some way. If they get no
feedback at all, they do tend to forget
stuff, which I get. So, it does seem
that the limitation on how long you can
keep them alive no longer is a problem.
For the longest time, people have been
figuring out how to vascularize them
because the idea was they couldn't
absorb enough oxygen to get to their
core. But it may be that they were just
bored and atrophying and eventually they
stopped sending out electrical signals
because they didn't work. They couldn't
communicate with the rest of the
organoid. These systems are very new and
there are definitely ethical concerns
about how much suffering might be
imparted on a tiny human brain. Now,
most of the researchers you'll talk to
are cautious to call them tiny brains.
About half 50/50 whenever I talk to
someone who works with these guys wants
to anthropomorphize them or not. But I
really do think that we should have the
conversation about what suffering might
mean. because as we are making them more
complex and allowing them to do more
tasks, it's possible we may get to a
point where suffering should be a
consideration. And I do think we should
have that conversation before we get
there because the technology is
improving. A lot of the most recent
research around them has been making
them more complex, giving them more cell
types, making them larger. It's quite
difficult to do because if you want to
make a brain, you know, it's kind of
designed to happen in a body. But the
more similar that we can get to a human
brain means it's going to be a better
research subject. It's going to be more
similar to us people if you want to do
things like test medications.
But with that and as we figure out how
to keep them entertained, there is
always a possibility that us humans may
inadvertently create suffering. And
that's a conversation worth having. I
think it's very difficult to be a
scientist and be excited for your own
work and how cool and how creepy it
really is and how much good it can do,
but there's kind of an issue with people
being scared of it. And you have to
balance scared of it with actual ethical
considerations. I was actually just
about to go on the monologue about brain
organoids not being conscious because
they don't have a sleepwake cycle. So,
they don't have the capacity to be
conscious and they don't have a brain
stem. But I checked on that information
and I was wrong. Yes, apparently brain
arenoids have circadian rhythm. I don't
know how to feel about that one and I'll
probably make a video just on this and
do some reading. But yeah, apparently
they do have something akin to rest and
wakefulness.
I mean, in the paper that I had talked
about where they had them play Pac-Man,
they certainly seemed to enjoy resting
for a bit after they were shocked
continuously until they got food. So,
they also got shocked much harder if
they got eaten by the ghost. I do feel
like that kind of research is a little
unethical, and I'm not sure why, but it
feels unethical. As always, these papers
will be linked. Um, there's also been
some research where they gave them
melatonin. I personally wish that I
slept much, so I'm jealous. I'll leave
you with this. People have compared them
to hemispherectomies. In a hemisphere
ectomy, at least more modern ones, it's
where they disconnect a portion of the
brain from the rest of the brain. This
can be done for a variety of reasons.
It's sometimes done for severe epilepsy
when other treatments haven't worked.
But they leave the old portion of the
brain in there. It's essentially in a
continuous sleep cycle. It has delta
brain wave that looks like someone who
is asleep not too different from the
brain organoids potentially conscious at
least in this case for human brains but
just cut off from it. I think that's a
reasonable consideration just what could
we make one day and maybe we should talk
about it before we get there because
brain organoids do have a fantastic
potential to do a whole lot of good and
yes other people want conscious robots
and I I kind of want them too but I I'm
conflicted. I just I want to see what
humans can make. Yeah, I kind of want to
play God and I get it. It's not super
ethical but it is interesting. Follow
for more.